Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: Morgan School, 2014 March 21; MS2388
  Panel discussion on the campaign in the late 1960s to establish a community-run school in the Adams Morgan neighborhood of Washington, D.C. Participants were parents, activists, teachers and other school personnel who were involved in that campaign. The panel of Morgan School supporters included Edward G. Jackson Sr., president of the Morgan PTA when this effort started, and later chair of the Morgan Community School Board and an Advisory Neighborhood Commissioner; Irene Elkin, then an Adams Morgan community activist and chair of the Schools Committee of the Adams Morgan Community Council; Marcus Raskin, co-founder of the Institute for Policy Studies; Harrison Owen, then executive director of the Adams Morgan Community Council; and teachers Dorothy L. Artis and Dorothy Chappell. Also participating were school personnel Joan Broadus and Ida Mae Beasley.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Thomas P. Morgan Community School inteview: Morgan School, overcrowding, Morgan Annex, 17th & Euclid, Bishop Marie Reid, Morgan Community School Board, Kenneth Haskins, Health center, interns, school committee,1966, white families, St. Margaret's Episcopal, Pilgrim Church, Head Start, Friday night dances, Adams Morgan Teen Council, Vera Stevens, Sonora Whitfield, Americanization School, petitions, IPA, Antioch College, team teaching, Superintendent Hansen, plan approved, 1967, Diane Josephson, Haskins Principal, 1968, teaching interns, college classes at Morgan, teaching third grade, school secretary, conflict between traditional teachers and hippie Antioch students, lots of press,., good then bad, teachers' union, petition drive, community control concept, best part: Haskins and the interns, Antioch Summer Institute, sensitivity training, chaos of school opening, Adams Community school 2 years later, Issac and Ruth Long, design of new Reid School, Topper Carew, Mr and Mrs Jackson appreciation.
- Interview: Murphy, Luci, 2012 October 12; MS2388
  Human rights activist and topical/jazz singer who for more than four decades has been the musical voice of progressive social justice movements in the District of Columbia. She graduated WIlson High School the spring of 1968, when Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Robert Kennedy were assassinated, and began a life of musical activism at that time.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Luci Murphy interview: 5th grade petition, music, St. Stephens and the Incarnation Episcopal Church, Mother Scott, Fr. William Wendt, Banneker Junior High School, colonial status, picket lines downtown, Malcom X, Puerto Rico, Wilson High, School, 1968, riots, party atmosphere, JFK assassination, LBJ, RFK, action mass, guitar mass, coffee houses,, African dance groups, folk music, Cellar Door, Free Arts Program, Topper Carew, Ronnie Karpen, Sophie's Parlor, Gerry Schwin, Howard University, New School of Afro-American Thought, Brown Paper Bag parties, Luci's mother, a song that needs singing, concern for connectiveness, University Neighborhoods Council, 12 year old volunteer, Woodley House, Big Brother Big Sister, field trips for kids, integration was a trick on the black community, black leaders now invisible, March on Washington, St. Stephens, Poor People's March,, Palestinian support, leaders in Pitt's Hotel, Letelier assassination, Luci did memorials, draft counselors, end of Viet Nam war, Radio Hanoi.
- Interview: Nahikian, Marie, 2016 May 11; MS2388
  Activist involved in struggles around fair and affordable housing, civil rights, the anti-war movement and local D.C. politics.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Marie Nahikian interview: civil rights and journalism activities at University in North Carolina, Arrive in Washington early 1970, neighborhood organizing, Adams-Morgan, Other neighborhood activists, Topper Carew, Milton Kotler, Irene Waskow, IPS, Richard Barnet, Global Reach, Executive Director, Adams-Morgan Organization (AMO), democratic neighborhood projects, fish-farming, Institute for Local Self-Reliance (ILSR), science and technology, Karl Hess, IPS, College Editors Conference in 1970 at Shoreham Hotel., Hog Farm, Conspiracy Trial defendants, other antiwar activists attend, hold Nixon Secretary of Interior Warren Hickel (speaker) accountable for Vietnam War and other misdeeds, Hickel later resigns, Black Panthers, Black Panthers Revolutionary Convention held in Washington DC end of 1970, staff writer for a scrap metal trade association, Huey Newton, Black Panthers, Karl Hess, scrap metal association credit card, disappearing rental car, Harassment by FBI, AMO serves as model for Advisory Neighborhood Commission (ANCs) still operating today, housing issues in Adams-Morgan in mid-70s, Big housing issue: major displacement of families as area gentrifies, gentrification, Other people involved in housing: Dorothy McGhee, Ron Clark of RAP Inc., Atty. Johnny Barnes, 1972 city tenant rights law passed, right of tenants to purchase homes, tenant conversion processes, tenant eviction controls, Marie ran for City Council 1978 but did not win, Became active in homeless issues in mid-70s, Marie had regular "DC Issues" radio show in 70s with former City Council member Johnny Wilson, Marie continues work on housing and homelessness at HUD and in Brooklyn and city of Philadelphia through 2016.
- Interview: Onion Earth, 2017 January 27; MS2388
  Information provided by the donor: Earth Onion was a women's improvisational theater group in Washington, D.C. from 1970 to 1975. It began through the Women's Liberation Movement and worked very closely with many other political groups and movements in the area. It performed extensively around the Washington, D.C. area and toured around the country for about three years.
  Information provided by the donor: Lynn (Glixon) Ditchfield, Julie Huff and Susie (Solf) Philips describe the creation of the Earth Onion Theater Group, which performed from 1970-75, the experiences of the group, its impact on themselves and others, its connections to the political and cultural movements of the time, reasons for its ending in 1975, and its long-term influence on them in the work each of them did in the following decades.
  Keywords provided by the donor: Women's theater group, Washington D.C., improvisational, 1970-75, Women's Liberation Movement, intentional community, Earth Angel, Earth Onion, free southern theater, women's liberation office turn to being anti male babies, play and dance, no meeting, no dogma and rhetoric, into our bodies, consciousness lowering, political theater, It's All Right to be Woman Theater, Caravan Theater, fringe theater, Woman Potion, Jamming, Earth Onion – peeling the layers, Three national tours, Elsa and the Tutnawald, Liberation, Utopia, perfect community of all women, Fort Bragg, FTA coffee house, political theater, San Francisco Mime Troupe, Bread and Puppet Theater - Goddard, Living theater, Becoming more professional, Learning the craft, Workshops, St. Elizabeth's, National Endowment for the Arts, Creative zone, Our lives, Rape, Abortion, Job interviews, Funny stories, Clothing, Improvisational, Audience real stories, New endings, Personal impact, Woman Potion, No single director, Wrote own pieces, Undocumented women, Workplace theater, Humor, Hard to reach people with theater, Social media, Film, Women's March 2017, Cuban Escambray Theater, People's stories, Trump communities, Welfare, Emilio Medici – Brazil President, Paulo Friere, Agitprop, guerrilla theater, workshops for other group, NLF birthday celebration, anti-war movement, skill building, taught skills, regular people, feminism, adornment, big media, pharmaceuticals, school-age women, sexualization of young women, self esteem, children's theater group, earth onion lessons and skills, healing, nurse, public health, roll play, STDs, workplace theater, teacher, emotionally disturbed youth, incarcerated youth, autism, collective, reasons for end of Earth Onion, communes, anti-war movements, collective health insurance, therapy coverage, live on limited means, camaraderie, inspirational work style, 35th reunion, interviews, importance of arts in social movements, novel about a theater group, arts-based immigration curriculum, gun control, grandchildren, poem on the end of Earth Onion, Carol Weissberg, Joanne Zonas
- Interview: Raskin, Marcus, 2013 January 07; MS2388
  (1934-2017) - Marcus Raskin was a prominent American social critic, political activist, intellectual, author, and philosopher. He was a leading figure in the Vietnam anti-war movement and the co-founder, with former State Department official Richard Barnet, of the progressive think tank, the Institute for Policy Studies (IPS), in Washington, D.C.
  A child prodigy on the piano, Raskin gave up a music career after receiving undergraduate and law degrees at the University of Chicago. Moving to Washington, D.C. in 1958, Raskin served as legislative counsel to a group of liberal congressmen. In 1961, he became assistant on national security affairs and disarmament as a member of the Special Staff of the National Security Council under President Kennedy's national security adviser McGeorge Bundy. In disagreement with the Kennedy administration's Cold War policies, Raskin left his government post to co-found IPS in 1963.
  The Vietnam War became a major area of concentration for Raskin and IPS. With noted scholar Bernard Fall, Raskin co-authored the Vietnam Reader, which was used in teach-ins against the war across the country. In 1967, he co-authored with Arthur Waskow, a colleague at IPS, "A Call to Resist Illegitimate Authority," which urged support for those who resisted the draft and the Vietnam War. The "Call to Resist" was signed by thousands of people, and because of it Raskin and Waskow took part in turning in 1,000 draft cards to the government. In 1968, Raskin was indicted -— along with William Sloane Coffin, Dr. Benjamin Spock, Michael Ferber and Mitchell Goodman—for conspiracy to aid resistance to the draft. The group became known as the "Boston Five." Raskin was acquitted.
  One of Raskin's children is Jamie Raskin, who was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives from Maryland's Eighth Congressional District in 2016 and was reelected in 2018.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Marcus Raskin interview: Jamie Raskin, Marcus Raskin, Sixties ran 1958-1975, California student march, End of Vietnam War, Martin Luther King Jr., Institute for Policy Studies, Richard (Dick) Barnet, IPS purpose — truth to power, IPS started 1963, Break-ins by government, Assassinations by Pinochet people, Deaths of colleagues, Ronni Moffitt, Worked White House, Special staff National Security Council, McGeorge Bundy, Special White House science group, War in Vietnam, Carl Kaysen, Deputy national security advisor, Falling out with Kaysen over Vietnam, Memorial service for Kaysen, "Conscience of NSC in White House", Dr. (Benjamin) Spock, "Spock Trial", Raised in Milwaukee, Musical talent — absolute pitch, Played piano, Started age 4, Studied at Juilliard, Franz Liszt, Vladimir Horowitz, Toscanini's daughter, Curtis Institute, Curtis Publishing Co., Rosina Lhevinne (teacher), Isabelle Vengerova (teacher ), Mother would open my mail, Brother captain in Air Force, World War II, Pianist Frank Glazer, University of Chicago Law School, Congressman Robert Kastenmeier, Rep. Leonard Wolf, A Call to Resist Illegitimate Authority, Basis for Criminal Information, Anti-Vietnam War Movement, Dr. Spock, Michael Ferber, Rev. William Sloane Coffin, Mitchell Goodman, Boston 5 case, New York Times, Conspiracy to aid and abet draft evasion, ACLU lawyers, Call to Resist, Legitimate authority, Justice and law, Say no to illegitimate authority, Burning draft cards, Turning in draft cards, Coffin, Chaplain at Yale University, Invited youths to burn draft cards, Boston 5 trial, Ferber, Coffin, Spock, Defendants' relationships, Ended up divorced or separated, Raskin acquitted, Devastated others found guilty, Telford Taylor, World War II war crimes prosecutor, Nuremberg prosecutor, In the Name of America (book), Seymour Melman - editor, Meeting - Deputy associate attorney general, Brought 270 draft cards to meeting, Arthur Waskow, Atrocities in Vietnam, In the Name of America, Ads New York Times, Signers, Jean-Paul Sartre, Simone de Beauvoir, Martin Luther King, IPS, Roger Wilkins, Nixon's Enemies List, Richard Barnet, Undercover agents, 58 informers at various IPS events, "J. Edgar Hoover wing" of the Communist Party, Resistance (document), John Cavanagh, 50th anniversary IPS, Mike Tabor, Allen Ginsberg, Ralph Nader, "Unsafe at Any Speed", New York Times, SDS, Jeff Faux, Spin-offs from IPS, Tina Smith, Women's movement, Off Our Backs, Richard Barnet, Gar Alperovitz, Barbara Ehrenreich, Ralph Nader, Roots of War (Barnet book), Alzheimer's (Richard B.), Anne Barnet, Border Crossings (Ann Barnet book), Jamie Raskin, Tommy Raskin.
- Interview: Riskin, Irv, 2012 December 21; MS2388
  (1918-2014) - Union organizer, McCarthy-era political witch-hunt victim, and life-long activist for peace and social justice. His Washington area activities included leadership in the Gray Panthers and the Grape Boycott, and as a key Washington Post strike supporter; and mentor to a generation of social justice activists in Washington, D.C.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Irv Riskin interview: Fred Solowey (interviewer), Irving Riskin, Red-diaper baby, Born August 18, 1918 Brooklyn, N.Y., father was member Communist Party, opposition to the Czar, father still in Russia 1905, concerned about treatment of Jews, father emigrated, father carpenter, cabinetmaker, IWW -- International Workers of the World, father active Scotsboro Boys case, Sacco-Vanzetti case, Italy invasion of Ethiopia, Great Depression -- father moved evicted people back into homes, Carpenters Union, father gave up his business to keep Communist Party membership, CP at the time barred membership to business owners, Communist teachers at his elementary school, First school to hire black teacher, Brooklyn College -- evening classes -- 2 years, IBEW (International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers), CIO (Congress of Industrial Organizations), AFL (American Federation of Labor), general strike (1937), Local 3 IBEW -- crossed picket lines, troublemaker and activist, Civil Service test for messenger job, Came to Washington, D.C. in 1939 as messenger, New Deal housing agency, Spain - Spanish Civil War, Abraham Lincoln Brigades, National Press Club (NPC), NPC cafeteria workers strike, Wife Suzanne supported strike, Longest strike at time -- 18 months, Cafeteria Workers Union, Communist Party D.C., Handed out leaflet anti-draft, anti-war (late 1930s), Socialist (Workers) Party, Trotskyists, Spanish Civil War, Came under suspicion, New Deal exciting period in D.C., CIO, messengers/clerks had longer work hours, organized messengers, Detroit -- went there 1944, Leon Keyserling, promotion from within policy, Suzanne (Riskin), administrator public housing Detroit 5 years, Detroit office no furniture, Ford Motor Company, Willow Run, Michigan planned community, UAW (United Auto Workers), Reutherites, Ford UAW Local, UAW Local cooperated with CP, Sis Cunningham, cultural program, 1946-1947, Local ejected from CIO, Walter Reuther, resigned administrator job, under Red-baiting pressure, Jimmy Hoffa, UPWA, union organizer, AFL, Teamsters, Hoffa promised not to raid Irv's union, moved to Allentown, Pennsylvania, wife's mother ran grocery/deli business, Riskin salesman for grocery business, Pennsylvania Communist Party, CP organizer for Allentown/Scranton area, FBI agent infiltrated local CP, Infiltrator was best friend for 10 years, Trial of Pennsylvania "Smith Act 11" or "Pennsylvania 6", Overthrowing government, Poisoning supply water in the area, FBI harassment, Allentown, Lost job at grocery/deli, Eddie Becker (camera operator), John Hanrahan (interviewer), Infiltrator later ran for various political offices, Infiltrator was courier for CP, Delivered notes party headquarters, Attended CP meetings, Infiltrator had access to everything in CP district, FBI, Philadelphia, party meeting materials, note of upcoming CP meeting in Philadelphia didn't reach Riskin, Infiltrator delivered CP notes to FBI, Riskin didn't get meeting notice, Riskin didn't attend meeting, Other CP sub-leadership arrested at meeting, Smith Act, Influenced by father re. CP, Influenced by CP members fighting for justice, Influenced by elementary school teachers who were "lefties", Party members outed in press, People crossed street to avoid him, stool pigeons, son Michael Riskin, 3rd grader -- not taken on school trip to fire station, Jewish community in Allentown, Irving Ezekiel Riskin -- full Jewish name, Herman Thomas -- informant's name, Suzanne Riskin, Working on Rosenberg case, House Un-American Activities Committee -- Suzanne called, HUAC, Senate Internal Security Subcommittee -- Irv, Selma Rein, David Rein, Took 5th Amendment, Moved family to Washington, D.C. in 1957, Suzanne relatives in D.C., Allentown comrades abandoned him, Only one gay comrade stood by him in Allentown, D.C. progressive community, grape boycott, D.C. segregation, CIO, Abe Bloom, peace movement, Women Strike for Peace, seasoned party (CP) people, Shul progressive Jewish Sunday School, teachers, members of left community, African American community, Jewish culture, history, Shul building on FBI list, Ruth Pinkson, CP property confiscated by government, IWO (International Workers Order), Maurice Jackson, Hudson Wells, under suspicion from party leadership, Pennsylvania 6 arrest -- I wasn't there, put me under suspicion, son Michael, daughter Karen, better for kids in D.C. -- made friends easily, Quaker summer camp and school, first interracial camp in Virginia, nuclear testing, civil rights movement, grape boycott, anti-Vietnam War, complacency in the 1950s, quite active in grape boycott, boycott house, vice president of Farm Workers union here permanently, worked with them, Ethel Weisser, Farmworkers grape boycott committee set up locally, peace movement, Gray Panthers, CIO, the Helen Miller case, youth movement, Eleanor Roosevelt, Youth Congress, Women Strike for Peace, Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case, Giles-Johnson case, Joe Forer, One of founders of Silver Spring Co-op, Bethesda, Md. (where lived), Washington Post pressmen's strike, Rainbow Coalition Montgomery County, Washington Hospital Center strike, Gray Panthers (Montgomery County), Abe Bloom, Anne Gallivan (interviewer), civil rights movement, grape boycott, distributed leaflets, Manuel Vasquez, Gene Boutilier, picketing Montgomery County Giant supermarket, scab grapes, Connecticut Avenue wine retailers, Gallo Wine, De Colores, the Joneses - singers -- Peter Jones and his brother Steve Jones, Peter wrote song about Gallo, Cesar Chavez, Dolores Huerta, AFL-CIO, Ethel Kennedy, Catholic activists, peace demonstrations, 1969 Mobilization, Farmworkers own problems, Paul Pumphrey, migrant workers, Carl Goldman, Gray Panthers, Maggie Kuhn, Vietnam War, mandatory retirement, Social Security, AARP, media ignored Gray Panthers, Montgomery County, county services, Social Security, Gray Panthers died off, Abe Bloom, head of Montgomery County Gray Panthers, 25 years, no new people coming along to Gray Panthers, children of Gray Panthers not involved, CIO unions, union lists of retired people, 1972 - no teaching medical hospital taught geriatric medicine, Maggie Kuhn, John Hanrahan (interviewer), Washington Post strike (Pressman's Union, Local 6), Fred Solowey, strike activist, strike support activities, divergent groups, Communists -- 4,5 variations of communists, couple labor groups, union v.p. asked -- who are the real communists here, publicity committee, Chip Berlet, Socialist Workers Party, Trotsky, Jim Dugan, Alliance for Labor and Community Action, Defense Committee, U.S. attorney's office, grand jury investigation, "conspiracy" to destroy The Washington Post, feeling for the union was so great, strikers understood unionism, Washington Star employee aided strike, Annapolis -- resolution supporting the strike, Maryland support committee, boycott the Post, cancel subscriptions, 2 car caravans supporting strike, pressman Zarbaugh, fundraiser, picketing Katharine Graham's house, favorable response, neighbors took leaflet, strike slogan -- "no grapes, no lettuce, no Post", Montgomery County musicians' union Local, government workers' unions, Carl Goldman, Kaufman Press, cancel subscriptions to the Post, Irv continued to boycott Post until his death, Jules Witcover, Mary McGrory, Washington Star, priest supported strike, "All the President's Men", Kennedy Center premiere, strikers shouting, 500 people protesting inside/outside, Eugene O'Sullivan, 2 strikers served time halfway house, benefit concert, Antioch law students, rally for Brookside miners, "Fighting Irv Riskin", Rainbow Coalition, Nicaraguan Coalition, Henry Wallace campaign, USO in WWII, Unions set up own USO in D.C. in WWII, 50 fairly active Pennsylvania communists.
- Interview: Robinson, Betty Garman, 2017 June 28; MS2388
  Betty Garman Robinson moved to Washington DC in 1965 to help run the SNCC office, then headed by Marion Barry, also new to town as National Chairman of SNCC. A graduate of Skidmore College and an early member of SNCC, Betty was already a dedicated civil rights activist and quickly became a key organizer for various initiatives of the "Free DC Movement" which was headed by Barry. Home Rule for DC was the overriding local civil rights issue in the 60s and 70s for Washingtonians. Later Betty assumed leadership positions in grassroots efforts to end the Vietnam War, including chairing the DC Committee to Defend the Conspiracy during the 1969-70 trial of antiwar leaders in Chicago, and her work in organizing a 1971 conference of Vietnamese, Cambodian and American women in Canada. Betty remains an active participant in the fight for racial justice, working with the anti-racist organization SURJ (Standing Up for Racial Justice) Hands on the Freedom Plow, published in 2010, is a collection of personal accounts by Betty and 51 other women about their experiences working in the civil rights movement.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Betty Garman Robinson interview: SNCC (Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee) in Washington, DC, Marion Barry, "Free DC" movement, Black Arts movement, Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis (ECTC), Anti-war movement, Women's Conference 1971 with Indochinese women, Madame Binh, Vietnamese revolutionary, Chicago Conspiracy Trial, Marxist Study Group, Move to Baltimore in late 1970s, Career in public health and safety, Other names mentioned in this interview: Melvin Deal, Tony Gittins, Topper Carew and the New Thing – all leaders in the DC Black Arts Movement, Hilda Mason – Long-time DC City Council member, local activist and head of DC Statehood Party, who attended 1971 conference and met Madame Binh.
- Interview: Rooney, Angela, 2013 February 19; MS2388
  (1920-2016) - Environmental and neighborhood activist. She was a leading figure in the 1960s and 1970s Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis (ECTC) which waged a successful anti-North Central Freeway / 3 Sisters Bridge campaign.